that's 400 million years old, one that's so ubiquitous that it operates in almost every ecosystem of the world, so huge that it can connect millions of traders simultaneously, and so persistent that it survived mass extinctions. It's here, right now, under our feet. You just can't see it. And unlike human economies that rely on cognition to make decisions, traders in this market, they beg, borrow, steal, cheat, all in the absence of thought. So hidden from our eyes, plant roots are colonized by a fungus called arbuscule mycorrhizae. Now the fungus forms these complex networks underground of fine filaments thinner than even threads of cotton. So follow one of these fungi, and it connects multiple plants simultaneously. You can think of it as an underground subway system, where each root is a station, where resources are loaded and unloaded. And it's also very dense, so roughly the length of many meters, even a kilometer, in a single gram of dirt. So that's the length of 10 football fields in just a thimbleful of soil. And it's everywhere. So if you passed over a tree, a shrub, a vine, even a tiny weed, you passed over a mycorrhizal network. Roughly 80 percent of all plant species are associated with these mycorrhizal fungi. So what does a root covered in fungi have to do with our global economy? And why as an evolutionary biologist have I spent the last 10 years of my life learning economic jargon? Well, the first thing you need to understand is that trade deals made by plant and fungal partners are surprisingly similar to those made by us, but perhaps even more strategic. You see, plant and fungal partners, they're not exchanging stocks and bonds, they're exchanging essential resources, and for the fungus, that's sugars and fats. It gets all of its carbon directly from the plant partner. So much carbon, so every year, roughly five billion tons of carbon from plants go into this network underground. For the root, what they need is phosphorus and nitrogen, so by exchanging their carbon they get access to all of the nutrients collected by that fungal network. So to make the trade, the fungus penetrates into the root cell of the host and forms a tiny structure called an arbuscule, which is Latin for "little tree." Now, you can think of this as the physical stock exchange of the trade market. So up until now, it seems very harmonious. Right? I scratch your back, you scratch mine, both partners get what they need. But here is where we need to pause and understand the power of evolution and natural selection. You see, there's no room for amateur traders on this market. Making the right trade strategy determines who lives and who dies. Now, I use the word strategy, but of course plant and fungi, they don't have brains. They're making these exchanges in the absence of anything that we would consider as thought. But, as scientists, we use behavioral terms such as strategy to describe behaviors to certain conditions, actions and reactions that are actually programmed into the DNA of the organism. So I started studying these trade strategies when I was 19 years old and I was living in the tropical rainforests of Panama. Now, everybody at the time was interested in this incredible diversity aboveground. And it was hyperdiversity. These are tropical rainforests. But I was interested in the complexity belowground. We knew that the networks existed, and we knew they were important, and I'm going to say it again, by important I mean important, so the basis of all plant nutrition for all the diversity that you do see aboveground. But at the time, we didn't know how these networks worked. We didn't know how they functioned. Why did only certain plants interact with certain fungi? So fast-forward to when I started my own group, and we really began to play with this trade market. You see, we would manipulate conditions. We would create a good trading partner by growing a plant in the sun and a poor trading partner by growing it in the shade. We would then connect these with a fungal network. And we found that the fungi were consistently good at discriminating among good and bad trading partners. They would allocate more resources to the host plant giving them more carbon. Now, we would run the reciprocal experiments where we would inoculate a host plant with good and bad fungi, and they were also good at discriminating between these trade partners. So what you have there is the perfect conditions for a market to emerge. It's a simple market, but it's a market nonetheless, where the better trading partner is consistently favored. But is it a fair market? Now this is where you need to understand that, like humans, plants and fungi are incredibly opportunistic. There's evidence that the fungus, once it penetrates into the plant cell, it can actually hijack the plant's own nutrient uptake system. It does this by suppressing the plant's own ability to take up nutrients from the soil. So this creates a dependency of the plant on the fungus. It's a false addiction, of sorts, whereby the plant has to feed the fungus just to get access to the resources right around its own root. There's also evidence that the fungi are good at inflating the price of nutrients. They do this by extracting the nutrients from the soil, but then rather than trading them with the host, they hoard them in their network, so this makes them unavailable to the plant and other competing fungi. So basic economics, as resource availability goes down, the value goes up. The plant is forced to pay more for the same amount of resources. But it's not all in favor of the fungus. Plants can be extremely cunning as well.
de 400 millones de años una tan ubicua que funciona en casi todos los ecosistemas del mundo, tan grande que puede conectar a millones de comerciantes simultáneamente, y tan persistente que sobrevivió a las extinciones masivas. Está aquí, ahora mismo, bajo nuestros pies. Simplemente no se puede ver. Y a diferencia de las economías humanas que dependen de la cognición para tomar decisiones, los comerciantes en este mercado, mendigan, piden prestado, roban, engañan, todo en ausencia de pensamiento. Muy escondido a nuestros ojos, las raíces de las plantas están colonizadas por un hongo llamado micorriza arbuscular. El hongo forma estas complejas redes subterráneas de filamentos finos más delgados, incluso, que hilos de algodón. Se sigue uno de estos hongos, y conecta múltiples plantas simultáneamente. Pueden pensarlo como un sistema de metro subterráneo, donde cada raíz es una estación, donde los recursos se cargan y descargan. Y también es muy denso, aproximadamente la longitud de muchos metros, incluso 1 km en un solo gramo de tierra. Esa es la longitud de 10 campos de fútbol. en solo un dedal de tierra. Y está en todas partes. Así, si pasaron por un árbol, un arbusto, una vid, incluso una pequeña hierba, pasaron por una red de micorrizas. Aproximadamente el 80 % de todas las especies de plantas está asociado con estos hongos micorrícicos. ¿Qué tiene que ver una raíz cubierta de hongos con nuestra economía global? ¿Y por qué como bióloga evolutiva he pasado los últimos 10 años de mi vida aprendiendo jerga económica? Lo primero que deben entender es que los acuerdos comerciales hechos por los socios plantas y hongos son sorprendentemente similares a los hechos por nosotros, pero quizás aún más estratégicos. Plantas y hongos socios, no están intercambiando acciones y bonos, están intercambiando recursos esenciales, y para el hongo, son azúcares y grasas. Obtiene todo su carbono directamente del socio planta. Cada año, aproximadamente cinco mil millones de toneladas de carbono de las plantas ingresan a esta red subterránea. Para la raíz, lo que se necesita es fósforo y nitrógeno, entonces intercambiando su carbono obtienen acceso a todos los nutrientes recolectados por esa red fúngica. Para hacer el intercambio, el hongo penetra en la célula raíz del huésped y forma una pequeña estructura llamada arbúsculo, que en latín significa "arbolito". Pueden pensar en esto como la bolsa de valores física del mercado comercial. Hasta ahora, parece muy armonioso. ¿Correcto? Te rasco la espalda, tú rascas la mía ambos socios obtienen lo que necesitan. Pero aquí es donde tenemos que hacer una pausa, para entender el poder de la evolución y la selección natural. No hay espacio para los comerciantes aficionados en este mercado. Hacer la estrategia comercial correcta determina quién vive y quién muere. Uso la palabra estrategia, pero, por supuesto, las plantas y los hongos no tienen cerebro. Hacen estos intercambios en ausencia de cualquier cosa que consideremos como pensamiento. Pero, como científicos, usamos términos de comportamiento como "estrategia" para describir comportamientos en ciertas condiciones, acciones y reacciones, que en realidad están programados en el ADN del organismo. Comencé a estudiar estas estrategias comerciales cuando tenia 19 años y vivía en las selvas tropicales de Panamá. Todos, entonces, estaban interesados en esta increíble diversidad en el terreno. Y era hiperdiversidad. Estas son las selvas tropicales. Pero yo estaba interesada en la complejidad subterránea. Sabíamos que las redes existían y que eran importantes, y voy a decirlo de nuevo, por importante quiero decir importante, ya que es la base de toda la nutrición vegetal y toda la diversidad que se ve en la superficie. Pero en ese momento, no sabíamos cómo funcionaban estas redes. No sabíamos cómo funcionaban. ¿Por qué solo ciertas plantas interactúan con ciertos hongos? Adelantemos a cuando comencé mi propio grupo, y realmente comenzamos a jugar con este mercado comercial. Verán, manipularíamos las condiciones. Creamos un buen socio comercial cultivando una planta al sol y un socio comercial pobre al cultivarlo a la sombra. Luego los conectaríamos con una red fúngica. Y descubrimos que los hongos eran consistentemente buenos en discriminar entre buenos y malos socios comerciales. Asignarían más recursos a la planta huésped dándoles más carbono. Ejecutamos los experimentos recíprocos en que inoculamos una planta huésped con hongos buenos y malos, y también fueron buenas para discriminar entre estos socios comerciales. Lo que se tiene allí son las condiciones perfectas para que surja un mercado. Es un mercado simple, pero, no obstante, es un mercado donde el mejor socio comercial es constantemente favorecido. ¿Pero es un mercado justo? Aquí es donde deben entender que, como los humanos, las plantas y los hongos son increíblemente oportunistas. Hay evidencia de que el hongo, una vez que penetra en la célula vegetal, en realidad puede secuestrar el sistema de absorción de nutrientes de la planta. Lo hace suprimiendo la capacidad de la planta. de tomar nutrientes del suelo. Esto crea una dependencia de la planta del hongo. Es una adicción falsa, de algún tipo, por lo que la planta tiene que alimentar al hongo solo para obtener acceso a los recursos alrededor de su propia raíz. También hay evidencia de que los hongos son buenos para inflar el precio de los nutrientes. Lo hacen extrayendo los nutrientes del suelo, pero luego, en lugar de intercambiarlos con el anfitrión, los acaparan en su red, haciendo que no estén disponibles para la planta y otros hongos competidores. Economía básica, a medida que la disponibilidad de recursos disminuye, el valor aumenta. La planta se ve obligada a pagar más por la misma cantidad de recursos. Pero no todo está a favor del hongo. Las plantas también pueden ser extremadamente astutas.
There are some orchids -- and I always think orchids somehow seem like the most devious of the plant species in the world -- and there are some orchids that just tap directly into the network and steal all their carbon. So these orchids, they don't even make green leaves to photosynthesize. They're just white. So rather than photosynthesizing, tap into the network, steal the carbon and give nothing in return. Now I think it's fair to say that these types of parasites also flourish in our human markets. So as we began to decode these strategies, we learned some lessons. And the first one was that there's no altruism in this system. There's no trade favors. We don't see strong evidence of the fungus helping dying or struggling plants unless it directly benefits the fungus itself. Now I'm not saying if this is good or bad. Unlike humans, a fungus, of course, cannot judge its own morality.
Hay algunas orquídeas. --y siempre pienso que las orquídeas parecen las más tortuosas de las especies de plantas en el mundo-- y hay algunas orquídeas que solo tocan directamente en la red y roban todo su carbono. Estas orquídeas, ni siquiera hacen hojas verdes para fotosintetizar. Son solo blancas. En lugar de fotosintetizar, aprovechan la red, roban el carbono y no dan nada a cambio. Creo que es justo decir que este tipo de parásitos también florece en nuestros mercados humanos. Cuando comenzamos a descodificar estas estrategias, aprendimos algunas lecciones. Y la primera fue que no hay altruismo en este sistema. No hay favores comerciales. No vemos evidencia fuerte del hongo que ayuda a las plantas moribundas o que luchan a menos que beneficie directamente al hongo en sí. No estoy diciendo si esto es bueno o malo. A diferencia de los humanos, un hongo, claro, no puede juzgar su moralidad.
And as a biologist, I'm not advocating for these types of ruthless neoliberal market dynamics enacted by the fungi. But the trade system, it provides us with a benchmark to study what an economy looks like when it's been shaped by natural selection for hundreds of millions of years in the absence of morality, when strategies are just based on the gathering and processing of information, uncontaminated by cognition: no jealousy, no spite, but no hope, no joy. So we've made progress
Y como bióloga, no estoy abogando por este tipo de dinámica despiadada del mercado neoliberal promulgada por los hongos. Pero el sistema de comercio, nos proporciona un punto de referencia para estudiar cómo se ve una economía cuando ha sido moldeada por selección natural por cientos de millones de años en ausencia de moralidad, cuando las estrategias solo se basan en la recopilación y el procesamiento de información, no contaminado por cognición: sin celos, sin rencor, pero no hay esperanza, no hay alegría. Así que hemos progresado
in decoding the most basic trade principles at this point, but as scientists we always want to take it one step further, and we're interested in more complex economic dilemmas. And specifically we're interested in the effects of inequality. So inequality has really become a defining feature of today's economic landscape. But the challenges of inequality are not unique to the human world. I think as humans we tend to think that everything's unique to us, but organisms in nature must face relentless variation in their access to resources. How does a fungus that can again be meters long change its trade strategy when it's exposed simultaneously to a rich patch and a poor patch? And, more generally, how do organisms in nature use trade to their advantage
al decodificar los principios comerciales más básicos en este punto, pero como científicos siempre queremos ir un paso más allá, y estamos interesados en dilemas económicos más complejos. Y específicamente estamos interesados en los efectos de la desigualdad. La desigualdad se ha convertido realmente en una característica definitoria del panorama económico actual. Pero los desafíos de la desigualdad no son exclusivos del mundo humano. Creo que como humanos tendemos a pensar que todo es único para nosotros, pero organismos en la naturaleza debe enfrentar una variación incesante en su acceso a los recursos. ¿Cómo funciona un hongo que nuevamente puede tener metros de largo para cambiar su estrategia comercial cuando se expone simultáneamente a una parcela rica y una pobre? Y, más generalmente, ¿cómo los organismos en la naturaleza utilizan el comercio en su beneficio
when they're faced with uncertainty in terms of their access to resources? Here's where I have to let you in on a secret: studying trade underground is incredibly difficult. You can't see where or when important trade deals take place. So our group helped pioneer a method, a technology, whereby we could tag nutrients with nanoparticles, fluorescing nanoparticles called quantum dots. What the quantum dots allow us to do is actually light up the nutrients so we can visually track their movements across the fungal network and into the host root. So this allows us finally to see the unseen, so we can study how fungi bargain at a small scale with their plant hosts. So to study inequality, we exposed a fungal network to these varying concentrations of fluorescing phosphorus, mimicking patches of abundance and scarcity across this artificial landscape. We then carefully quantified fungal trade. And we found two things. The first thing we found was that inequality encouraged the fungus to trade more. So I can use the word "encouraged" or "stimulated" or "forced," but the bottom line is that compared to control conditions, inequality was associated with higher levels of trade. This is important, because it suggests that evolving a trade partnership in nature can help organisms cope with the uncertainty of accessing resources. Second, we found that, exposed to inequality, the fungus would move resources from the rich patch of the network, actively transport them to the poor side of the network. Now, of course, we could see this because the patches were fluorescing in different colors. So at first, this result was incredibly puzzling. Was it to help the poor side of the network? No. We found that the fungus gained more by first moving the resources to where demand was higher. Simply by changing where across the network the fungus was trading, it could manipulate the value of those resources. Now this stimulated us to really dig deeper into how information is shared. It suggests a high level of sophistication, or at least a medium level of sophistication in an organism with no cognition. How is it that a fungus can sense market conditions across its network and then make calculations of where and when to trade? So we wanted to look about information and how it's shared across this network, how the fungus integrates cues. So to do that, what you need to do is dive deep in and get a higher resolution into the network itself. We began to study complex flows inside the hyphal network. So what you're looking at right now is a living fungal network
cuando se enfrentan a la incertidumbre en cuanto a su acceso a los recursos? Aquí es donde tengo que contarles un secreto: estudiar comercio subterráneo es increíblemente difícil. No puede ver dónde o cuándo tienen lugar importantes acuerdos comerciales. Entonces nuestro grupo ayudó a crear un método, una tecnología, por la que podríamos etiquetar nutrientes con nanopartículas, nanopartículas fluorescentes llamadas puntos cuánticos. Lo que los puntos cuánticos nos permiten hacer es en realidad iluminar los nutrientes para que podamos seguir visualmente sus movimientos a través de la red fúngica y en la raíz del anfitrión. Esto nos permite finalmente ver lo invisible, para que podamos estudiar cómo los hongos negocian a pequeña escala con sus plantas anfitrionas. Para estudiar la desigualdad, expusimos una red fúngica a estas concentraciones variables de fósforo fluorescente, imitando parcelas de abundancia y escasez a través de este paisaje artificial. Luego cuantificamos cuidadosamente el comercio de hongos. Y encontramos dos cosas. Lo primero que encontramos fue que la desigualdad alentó al hongo a comerciar más. Puedo usar la palabra "alentado" o "estimulado" o "forzado", pero la conclusión es que, en comparación con las condiciones de control, la desigualdad se asoció con mayores niveles de comercio. Esto es importante, porque sugiere que evolucionar una asociación comercial en la naturaleza puede ayudar a hacer frente a los organismos, a la incertidumbre de acceder a los recursos. En segundo lugar, encontramos que, expuesto a la desigualdad, el hongo movería recursos de la parcela rica de la red, transportarlos activamente al lado pobre de la red. Por supuesto, podríamos ver esto porque las parcelas estaban fluorescentes en diferentes colores. Al principio, este resultado fue increíblemente desconcertante. ¿Fue para ayudar al lado pobre de la red? No. Descubrimos que el hongo ganó más al mover primero los recursos. a donde la demanda era mayor. Simplemente cambiando en qué parte de la red se comercializaba el hongo, podría manipular el valor de esos recursos. Esto nos estimuló a profundizar más en cómo se comparte la información. Sugiere un alto nivel de sofisticación, o al menos un nivel medio de sofisticación en un organismo sin cognición. ¿Cómo es que un hongo puede detectar las condiciones del mercado en toda su red y luego hacer cálculos de dónde y cuándo comerciar? Así que queríamos buscar información y cómo se comparte en esta red, cómo el hongo integra las señales. Para hacerlo, hay que sumergirse profundamente y obtener una resolución más alta en la red misma. Comenzamos a estudiar flujos complejos dentro de la red de hifas. Lo que están viendo ahora es una red fúngica viva
with the cellular contents moving across it. This is happening in real time, so you can see the time stamp up there. So this is happening right now. This video isn't sped up. This is what is happening under our feet right now. And there's a couple of things that I want you to notice. It speeds up, it slows down, it switches directions. So we're working now with biophysicists to try to dissect this complexity. How is the fungus using these complex flow patterns to share and process information and make these trade decisions? Are fungi better at making trade calculations than us? Now here's where we can potentially borrow models from nature. We're increasingly reliant on computer algorithms to make us profitable trades in split-second time scales. But computer algorithms and fungi, they both operate in similar, uncognitive ways. The fungi just happens to be a living machine. What would happen if we compare and compete the trading strategies of these two? Who would win?
con el contenido celular moviéndose a través de él. Esto está sucediendo en tiempo real; pueden ver la marca de tiempo allí arriba. Esto está sucediendo ahora. Este video no está acelerado. Esto está sucediendo bajo nuestros pies ahora. Y hay un par de cosas que quiero que noten. Se acelera, se ralentiza, cambia de dirección. Ahora estamos trabajando con biofísicos para tratar de diseccionar esta complejidad. ¿Cómo utiliza el hongo estos complejos patrones de flujo para compartir y procesar información y tomar estas decisiones comerciales? ¿Los hongos son mejores para hacer cálculos comerciales que nosotros? Aquí es donde potencialmente podemos tomar prestados modelos de la naturaleza. Dependemos cada vez más de los algoritmos informáticos. para hacernos negocios rentables en escalas de tiempo de fracción de segundo. Pero los algoritmos informáticos y los hongos, ambos operan de manera similar, sin cognición. Los hongos resultan ser una máquina viviente. ¿Qué pasaría si comparamos y hacemos competir las estrategias comerciales de estos dos? ¿Quién ganaría?
The tiny capitalist that's been around since before and the fall of the dinosaurs? My money is on the fungus. Thank you. (Applause)
¿El pequeño capitalista que ha existido desde antes de la caída de los dinosaurios? Mi dinero está con el hongo. Gracias. (Aplausos)